Guide to the Joseph Wheaton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Joseph Wheaton papers
1797-1839
MS 631
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Correspondence and documents between Major Joseph Wheaton, members of his family, and various government officials concerning attempts to secure reimbursement from the government for debts incurred while Wheaton was serving as Deputy Quarter Master General during the War of 1812. Correspondents of note include Joseph Bloomfield, William Eustis, Charles Gratiot, George Hay, Thomas Jefferson, Lafayette, Return Jonathan Meigs, James Monroe, Amos Stoddard, and Martin Van Buren.
Wheaton, Joseph, 1755-1828
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1966.
Scope and Contents
The Joseph Wheaton Papers, 1797-1839, consist of correspondence and documents that passed between Major Wheaton, members of his family, and various government officials. The materials relate to attempts by Wheaton and his family to obtain reimbursement for debts incurred while he was serving as Deputy Quarter Master General during the War of 1812. Some of the later correspondence involves James Monroe Burke (1801-1859), a son-in-law of Joseph Wheaton, who was an official in the Treasury Department.
Joseph Wheaton was born in New York in 1755 of English parents. At the age of twenty he enlisted in the Second Rhode Island Line. In August of 1779 he became a lieutenant in the First Rhode Island Line, retained in Olney's Rhode Island Battalion. On the recommendation of General Washington, he then went to the State Continental Battalion where he served from January, 1781 to December, 1783. After this his activities are somewhat difficult to document, but it is obvious from the papers in this collection that he was serving in the office of the Quarter Master General during the War of 1812. Joseph Wheaton died November 23, 1828, probably in Washington, D. C.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph Wheaton: in 1775 enlisted in Second Rhode Island Line; in 1779 became a lieutenant in Olney's Rhode Island Brigade; served in the State Continental Battalion, 1781-1783; served in office of the Quarter Master General during the War of 1812; attained the rank of Major.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged alphabetically by the name of the correspondent with a group of documents and miscellany falling at the end of the arrangement.
Armed Forces; United States -- History -- War of 1812; Soldiers; Bloomfield, Joseph, 1753-1823; Burke, James Monroe, 1801-1859; Crawford, William Harris, 1772-1834; Eustis, William, 1753-1825; Gratiot, Charles, 1786-1855; Hay, George, 1765-1830; Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1764-1825; Monroe, James, 1758-1831; Stoddard, Amos, 1762-1813; Van Buren, John, 1810-1866; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862; Wheaton, Joseph, 1755-1828; Burke family
- Anderson, Joseph, (1752-1837)
  - Recommendation for Joseph Wheaton (also signed by others), 1812 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autograph letter signed to President Jackson, 1832 April 13; 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bloomfield, Joseph (1753-1823), autograph letter signed to Wheaton, 1813 November 7; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes a typed copy of the letter.
- Burke, Edmund (U.S.N.), invitation to Mrs. Wheaton, 1797 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Burke, John, autograph letter signed to Burke from Wheaton, 1815 December 2; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Chillicothe, Ohio. Merchants Bank, autograph letter signed to Joseph Wheaton signed by the President and directors, 1813 October 1; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Crawford, William Harris (1772-1834), autograph letter signed to Crawford from Wheaton, 1816 February 26; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Cutts, Mrs. C., two invitations to James Burke, No year, April 6; no year, December 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Eustis, William, (1753-1825)
  - Autograph letter signed to Wheaton, 1812 August 14; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 8 autograph letters signed to Eustis from Wheaton, 1812 August 27 - October 6, 1823 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Everett, C., autograph letter signed (true copy) to John C. Calhoun, 1823 August 25; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Gooch, Claiboune W., 4 autograph letters signed to Wheaton, 1824 March 23 - November 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Graham, George, autograph letter signed to Wheaton, 1815 October 5; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Gratiot, Charles, (1788-1855)
  - 3 autograph letters signed to Wheaton, 1813 January 1 - April 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Statement regarding Wheaton, 1818 August 3; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Green, Moses, autograph letter signed to Wheaton (written for Green by William W. Hening), 1831 December 21; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hay, George, (1765-1830), autograph letter signed to Hay from Wheaton, 1823 June (no day); 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Jefferson, Thomas, President U.S., (1743-1826), autograph letter signed to Wheaton, 1814 January 29; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roche Gilbert du Matier, marquis de, (1757-1834), autograph letter signed to Wheaton, [1825] January 19; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Maurice, James, autograph letter signed to Wheaton, 1814 October 10; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Meigs, Return Jonathan (1764-1824), autograph letter signed to Wheaton, 1815 February 13; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Monroe, James, President U.S., (1758-1831)
  - 3 autograph letters signed to Wheaton, 1814 November 29 - 1815 July 29, no year January 25 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 2 autograph letters signed to Monroe from Wheaton undated cover, 1822 December 5, 1823 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Phinney, Patience, autograph note to Miss Monroe, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Piatt, W., 2 autograph letters signed to Wheaton, 1813 January 7, January 12 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Rind, William A., autograph letter signed to James M. Burke, 1834 February 10; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Includes cover and genealogical notes on back of letter.
- Stanard, [Robert, Conway?], autograph letter signed to Wheaton, 1815 March 8; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Stoddard, Amos (1762-1813), autograph letter signed to Wheaton, 1812 August 15; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Swan, William
  - Autograph letter signed to Wheaton, 1815 February 3; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Autograph letter signed (copy) to James Monroe, 1815 February 6; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 25)
- U.S. Adjutant General's Office, extract of general order, 1815 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- U.S. House of Representatives, autograph letter signed (with Petition) to Speaker of the House of Representatives from Wheaton, 1821 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- U.S. War Department. Pension Office, autograph letter signed to Mrs. Samuel Handy regarding Joseph Wheaton's pension, 1837 July 26; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Van Buren, John, (1810-1866)
  - Autograph letter signed to James M. Burke, 1839 August 15; 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Autograph letter signed to Mr. Vail, 1839 September 23; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Van Buren, Martin, President U.S., (1782-1862)
  - Autograph letter signed to Mrs. Mary Burke, 1831 August 15; 5 pages (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Autograph note to Sarah Burke, 1833 March 30; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Autograph letter signed to James Burke, [1841] January 5; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Autograph letter signed, appointment, to James Burke, 1841 January 11; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Van Buren, Martin, Jr., 3 autograph letters signed to James Burke undated cover, [1831] August 27- 1838 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Van Buren, Smith Thompson, autograph letter signed to James Burke, 1836 March 29; 1 page (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Wheaton, Joseph, (1755-1828) documents regarding his claim
  - Appeal to the House of Representatives, 1820 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Petition, 1820 November 25?; 22 pages (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Remarks on claim of Wheaton by Peter Hagner (auditor) "No. 4", 1819 March 11 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Account of Wheaton (stated true amount due him) "A", circa 1815-circa 1819 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Copy of letter from Graham to Wheaton "B", 1815 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Statement of differences in account settled "C", 1819 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Wheaton - personal account "C", 1815 April-1817 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Report of third auditor with autograph letter (copy) G.B. Cooke to Secretary of War, 1815 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Report of third auditor, 1819 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Statement no. 1, Accompanying report of third auditor dated 1819 Dec 27 on the petition of Joseph Wheaton, 1819 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Statement no. 3, Accompanying report of third auditor on petition on petition of Joseph Wheaton, 1819 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous documents regarding claim of Major Wheaton (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Williams, Lewis, autographed letter signed to Williams from Wheaton, 1820 December 5; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Miscellaneous
  - List of the governors of Maryland, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Typed genealogical notes on Burke - Wheaton families, circa 1797-circa 1839 (Box 1, Folder 36)